<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book name="Additions to Esther" slug="additions-to-esther" chapterCount="6" verseCount="250" translation="Catholic Public Domain Version" abbreviation="CPDV">
  <chapter number="1" verseCount="12">
    <verse number="1" reference="Additions to Esther 1:1">In the fourth year of the reign of Ptolemy and Cleopatra, Dositheus, who said he was a priest, and of the Levitical race, and Ptolemy his son brought this epistle of Phurim, which they said Lysimachus the son of Ptolemy had interpreted in Jerusalem.</verse>
    <verse number="2" reference="Additions to Esther 1:2">In the second year of the reign of Artaxerxes the great, in the first day of the month Nisan, Mardochai the son of Jair, the son of Semei, the son of Cis, of the tribe of Benjamin:</verse>
    <verse number="3" reference="Additions to Esther 1:3">A Jew who dwelt in the city of Susan, a great man and among the first of the king's court, had a dream.</verse>
    <verse number="4" reference="Additions to Esther 1:4">Now he was of the number of the captives, whom Nabuchodonosor king of Babylon had carried away from Jerusalem with Jechonias king of Juda:</verse>
    <verse number="5" reference="Additions to Esther 1:5">And this was his dream: Behold there were voices, and tumults, and thunders, and earthquakes, and a disturbance upon the earth.</verse>
    <verse number="6" reference="Additions to Esther 1:6">And behold two great dragons came forth ready to fight one against another.</verse>
    <verse number="7" reference="Additions to Esther 1:7">And at their cry all nations were stirred up to fight against the nation of the just.</verse>
    <verse number="8" reference="Additions to Esther 1:8">And that was a day of darkness and danger, of tribulation and distress, and great fear upon the earth.</verse>
    <verse number="9" reference="Additions to Esther 1:9">And the nation of the just was troubled fearing their own evils, and was prepared for death.</verse>
    <verse number="10" reference="Additions to Esther 1:10">And they cried to God: and as they were crying, a little fountain grew into a very great river, and abounded into many waters.</verse>
    <verse number="11" reference="Additions to Esther 1:11">The light and the sun rose up, and the humble were exalted, and they devoured the glorious.</verse>
    <verse number="12" reference="Additions to Esther 1:12">And when Mardochai had seen this, and arose out of his bed, he was thinking what God would do: and he kept it fixed in his mind, desirous to know what the dream should signify.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="2" verseCount="6">
    <verse number="1" reference="Additions to Esther 2:1">And he abode at that time in the king's court with Bagatha and Thara the king's eunuchs, who were porters of the palace.</verse>
    <verse number="2" reference="Additions to Esther 2:2">And when he understood their designs, and had diligently searched into their projects, he learned that they went about to lay violent hands on king Artaxerxes, and he told the king thereof.</verse>
    <verse number="3" reference="Additions to Esther 2:3">Then the king had them both examined, and after they had confessed, commanded them to be put to death.</verse>
    <verse number="4" reference="Additions to Esther 2:4">But the king made a record of what was done: and Mardochai also committed the memory of the thing to writing.</verse>
    <verse number="5" reference="Additions to Esther 2:5">And the king commanded him, to abide in the court of the palace, and gave him presents for the information.</verse>
    <verse number="6" reference="Additions to Esther 2:6">But Aman the son of Amadathi the Bugite was in great honour with the king, and sought to hurt Mardochai and his people, because of the two eunuchs of the king who were put to death.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="3" verseCount="18">
    <verse number="1" reference="Additions to Esther 3:1">And this was the copy of the letter: Artaxerxes the great king who reigneth from India to Ethiopia, to the princes and governors of the hundred and twenty-seven provinces, that are subject to his empire, greeting.</verse>
    <verse number="2" reference="Additions to Esther 3:2">Whereas I reigned over many nations, and had brought all the world under my dominion, I was not willing to abuse the greatness of my power, but to govern my subjects with clemency and that they might live quietly without any terror, and might enjoy peace, which is desired by all men,</verse>
    <verse number="3" reference="Additions to Esther 3:3">But when I asked my counsellors how this might be accomplished, one that excelled the rest in wisdom and fidelity, and was second after the king, Aman by name,</verse>
    <verse number="4" reference="Additions to Esther 3:4">Told me that there was a people scattered through the whole world, which used new laws, and acted against the customs of all nations, despised the commandments of kings, and violated by their opposition the concord of all nations.</verse>
    <verse number="5" reference="Additions to Esther 3:5">Wherefore having learned this, and seeing one nation in opposition to all mankind using perverse laws, and going against our commandments, and disturbing the peace and concord of the provinces subject to us,</verse>
    <verse number="6" reference="Additions to Esther 3:6">We have commanded that all whom Aman shall mark out, who is chief over all the provinces, and second after the king, and whom we honour as a father, shall be utterly destroyed by their enemies, with their wives and children, and that none shall have pity on them, on the fourteenth day of the twelfth month Adar of this present year:</verse>
    <verse number="7" reference="Additions to Esther 3:7">That these wicked men going down to hell in one day, may restore to our empire the peace which they had disturbed.</verse>
    <verse number="8" reference="Additions to Esther 3:8">But Mardochai besought the Lord, remembering all his works,</verse>
    <verse number="9" reference="Additions to Esther 3:9">And said: O Lord, Lord, almighty king, for all things are in thy power, and there is none that can resist thy will, if thou determine to save Israel.</verse>
    <verse number="10" reference="Additions to Esther 3:10">Thou hast made heaven and earth and all things that are under the cope of heaven.</verse>
    <verse number="11" reference="Additions to Esther 3:11">Thou art Lord of all, and there is none that can resist thy majesty.</verse>
    <verse number="12" reference="Additions to Esther 3:12">Thou knowest all things, and thou knowest that it was not out of pride and or any desire of glory, that I refused to worship the proud Aman,</verse>
    <verse number="13" reference="Additions to Esther 3:13">(For I would willingly and readily for the salvation of Israel have kissed even the steps of his feet,)</verse>
    <verse number="14" reference="Additions to Esther 3:14">But I feared lest I should transfer the honour of my God to a man, and lest I should adore any one except my God.</verse>
    <verse number="15" reference="Additions to Esther 3:15">And now, O Lord, O king, O God of Abraham, have mercy on thy people, because our enemies resolve to destroy us, and extinguish thy inheritance.</verse>
    <verse number="16" reference="Additions to Esther 3:16">Despise not thy portion, which thou hast redeemed for thyself out of Egypt.</verse>
    <verse number="17" reference="Additions to Esther 3:17">Hear my supplication, and be merciful to thy lot and inheritance, and turn our mourning into joy, that we may live and praise thy name, O Lord, and shut not the mouths of them that sing to thee.</verse>
    <verse number="18" reference="Additions to Esther 3:18">And all Israel with like mind and supplication cried to the Lord, because they saw certain death hanging over their heads.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="4" verseCount="19">
    <verse number="1" reference="Additions to Esther 4:1">Queen Esther also, fearing the danger that was at hand, had recourse to the Lord.</verse>
    <verse number="2" reference="Additions to Esther 4:2">And when she had laid away her royal apparel, she put on garments suitable for weeping and mourning: instead of divers precious ointments, she covered her head with ashes and dung, and she humbled her body with fasts: and all the places in which before she was accustomed to rejoice, she filled with her torn hair.</verse>
    <verse number="3" reference="Additions to Esther 4:3">And she prayed to the Lord the God of Israel, saying: O my Lord, who alone art our king, help me a desolate woman, and who have no other helper but thee.</verse>
    <verse number="4" reference="Additions to Esther 4:4">My danger is in my hands.</verse>
    <verse number="5" reference="Additions to Esther 4:5">I have heard of my father that thou, O Lord, didst take Israel from among all nations, and our fathers from all their predecessors, to possess them as an everlasting inheritance, and thou hast done to them as thou hast promised.</verse>
    <verse number="6" reference="Additions to Esther 4:6">We have sinned in thy sight, and therefore thou hast delivered us into the hands of our enemies:</verse>
    <verse number="7" reference="Additions to Esther 4:7">For we have worshipped their gods. Thou art just, O Lord.</verse>
    <verse number="8" reference="Additions to Esther 4:8">And now they are not content to oppress us with most hard bondage, but attributing the strength of their hands to the power of their idols.</verse>
    <verse number="9" reference="Additions to Esther 4:9">They design to change thy promises, and destroy thy inheritance, and shut the mouths of them that praise thee, and extinguish the glory of thy temple and altar,</verse>
    <verse number="10" reference="Additions to Esther 4:10">That they may open the mouths of Gentiles, and praise the strength of idols, and magnify for ever a carnal king.</verse>
    <verse number="11" reference="Additions to Esther 4:11">Give not, O Lord, thy sceptre to them that are not, lest they laugh at our ruin: but turn their counsel upon themselves, and destroy him that hath begun to rage against us.</verse>
    <verse number="12" reference="Additions to Esther 4:12">Remember, O Lord, and shew thyself to us in the time of our tribulation, and give me boldness, O Lord, king of gods, and of all power:</verse>
    <verse number="13" reference="Additions to Esther 4:13">Give me a well ordered speech in my mouth in the presence of the lion, and turn his heart to the hatred of our enemy, that both he himself may perish, and the rest that consent to him.</verse>
    <verse number="14" reference="Additions to Esther 4:14">But deliver us by thy hand, and help me, who have no other helper, but thee, O Lord, who hast the knowledge of all things.</verse>
    <verse number="15" reference="Additions to Esther 4:15">And thou knowest that I hate the glory of the wicked, and abhor the bed of the uncircumcised, and of every stranger.</verse>
    <verse number="16" reference="Additions to Esther 4:16">Thou knowest my necessity, that I abominate the sign of my pride and glory, which is upon my head in the days of my public appearance, and detest it as a menstruous rag, and wear it not in the days of my silence,</verse>
    <verse number="17" reference="Additions to Esther 4:17">And that I have not eaten at Aman's table, nor hath the king's banquet pleased me, and that I have not drunk the wine of the drink offerings:</verse>
    <verse number="18" reference="Additions to Esther 4:18">And that thy handmaid hath never rejoiced, since I was brought hither unto this day but in thee, O Lord, the God of Abraham.</verse>
    <verse number="19" reference="Additions to Esther 4:19">O God, who art mighty above all, hear the voice of them, that have no other hope, and deliver us from the hand of the wicked, and deliver me from my fear.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="5" verseCount="19">
    <verse number="1" reference="Additions to Esther 5:1">And he commanded her (no doubt but he was Mardochai) to go to the king, and petition for her people, and for her country.</verse>
    <verse number="2" reference="Additions to Esther 5:2">Remember, (said he,) the days of thy low estate, how thou wast brought up by my hand, because Aman the second after the king hath spoken against us unto death.</verse>
    <verse number="3" reference="Additions to Esther 5:3">And do thou call upon the Lord, and speak to the king for us, and deliver us from death.</verse>
    <verse number="4" reference="Additions to Esther 5:4">And on the third day she laid away the garments she wore, and put on her glorious apparel.</verse>
    <verse number="5" reference="Additions to Esther 5:5">And glittering in royal robes, after she had called upon God the ruler and Saviour of all, she took two maids with her,</verse>
    <verse number="6" reference="Additions to Esther 5:6">And upon one of them she leaned, as if for delicateness and overmuch tenderness she were not able to bear up her own body.</verse>
    <verse number="7" reference="Additions to Esther 5:7">And the other maid followed her lady, bearing up her train flowing on the ground.</verse>
    <verse number="8" reference="Additions to Esther 5:8">But she with a rosy colour in her face, and with gracious and bright eyes hid a mind full of anguish, and exceeding great fear.</verse>
    <verse number="9" reference="Additions to Esther 5:9">So going in she passed through all doors in order, and stood before the king, where he sat upon his royal throne, clothed with his royal robes, and glittering with gold, and precious stones, and he was terrible to behold.</verse>
    <verse number="10" reference="Additions to Esther 5:10">And when he had lifted up his countenance, and with burning eyes had shewn the wrath of his heart, the queen sunk down, and her colour turned pale, and she rested her weary head upon her handmaid.</verse>
    <verse number="11" reference="Additions to Esther 5:11">And God changed the king's spirit into mildness, and all in haste and in fear he leaped from his throne, and holding her up in his arms, till she came to herself, caressed her with these words:</verse>
    <verse number="12" reference="Additions to Esther 5:12">What is the matter, Esther? I am thy brother, fear not.</verse>
    <verse number="13" reference="Additions to Esther 5:13">Thou shalt not die: for this law is not made for thee, but for all others.</verse>
    <verse number="14" reference="Additions to Esther 5:14">Come near then, and touch the sceptre.</verse>
    <verse number="15" reference="Additions to Esther 5:15">And as she held her peace, he took the golden sceptre, and laid it upon her neck, and kissed her, and said: Why dost thou not speak to me?</verse>
    <verse number="16" reference="Additions to Esther 5:16">She answered: I saw thee, my lord, as an angel of God, and my heart was troubled for fear of thy majesty.</verse>
    <verse number="17" reference="Additions to Esther 5:17">For thou, my lord, art very admirable, and thy face is full of graces.</verse>
    <verse number="18" reference="Additions to Esther 5:18">And while she was speaking, she fell down again, and was almost in a swoon.</verse>
    <verse number="19" reference="Additions to Esther 5:19">But the king was troubled, and all his servants comforted her.</verse>
  </chapter>
  <chapter number="6" verseCount="176">
    <verse number="1" reference="Additions to Esther 6:1">The great king Artaxerxes, from India to Ethiopia, to the governors and princes of a hundred and twenty-seven provinces, which obey our command, sendeth greeting. From India to Ethiopia... That is, who reigneth from India to Ethiopia.</verse>
    <verse number="2" reference="Additions to Esther 6:2">Many have abused unto pride the goodness of princes, and the honour that hath been bestowed upon them:</verse>
    <verse number="3" reference="Additions to Esther 6:3">And not only endeavour to oppress the king's subjects, but not bearing the glory that is given them, take in hand, to practise also against them that gave it.</verse>
    <verse number="4" reference="Additions to Esther 6:4">Neither are they content not to return thanks for benefits received, and to violate in themselves the laws of humanity, but they think they can also escape the justice of God who seeth all things.</verse>
    <verse number="5" reference="Additions to Esther 6:5">And they break out into so great madness, as to endeavour to undermine by lies such as observe diligently the offices committed to them, and do all things in such manner as to be worthy of all men's praise,</verse>
    <verse number="6" reference="Additions to Esther 6:6">While with crafty fraud they deceive the ears of princes that are well meaning, and judge of others by their own nature.</verse>
    <verse number="7" reference="Additions to Esther 6:7">Now this is proved both from ancient histories, and by the things which are done daily, how the good designs of kings are depraved by the evil suggestions of certain men.</verse>
    <verse number="8" reference="Additions to Esther 6:8">Wherefore we must provide for the peace of all provinces.</verse>
    <verse number="9" reference="Additions to Esther 6:9">Neither must you think, if we command different things, that it cometh of the levity of our mind, but that we give sentence according to the quality and necessity of times, as the profit of the commonwealth requireth.</verse>
    <verse number="10" reference="Additions to Esther 6:10">Now that you may more plainly understand what we say, Aman the son of Amadathi, a Macedonian both in mind and country, and having nothing of the Persian blood, but with his cruelty staining our goodness, was received being a stranger by us:</verse>
    <verse number="11" reference="Additions to Esther 6:11">And found our humanity so great towards him, that he was called our father, and was worshipped by all as the next man after the king:</verse>
    <verse number="12" reference="Additions to Esther 6:12">But he was so far puffed up with arrogancy, as to go about to deprive us of our kingdom and life.</verse>
    <verse number="13" reference="Additions to Esther 6:13">For with certain new and unheard of devices he hath sought the destruction of Mardochai, by whose fidelity and good services our life was saved, and of Esther the partner of our kingdom with all their nation:</verse>
    <verse number="14" reference="Additions to Esther 6:14">Thinking that after they were slain, he might work treason against us left alone without friends, and might transfer the kingdom of the Persians to the Macedonians.</verse>
    <verse number="15" reference="Additions to Esther 6:15">But we have found that the Jews, who were by that most wicked man appointed to be slain, are in no fault at all, but contrariwise, use just laws,</verse>
    <verse number="16" reference="Additions to Esther 6:16">And are the children of the highest and the greatest, and the ever living God, by whose benefit the kingdom was given both to our fathers and to us, and is kept unto this day.</verse>
    <verse number="17" reference="Additions to Esther 6:17">Wherefore know ye that those letters which he sent in our name, are void and of no effect.</verse>
    <verse number="18" reference="Additions to Esther 6:18">For which crime both he himself that devised it, and all his kindred hang on gibbets, before the gates of this city Susan: not we, but God repaying him as he deserved.</verse>
    <verse number="19" reference="Additions to Esther 6:19">But this edict, which we now send, shall be published in all cities, that the Jews may freely follow their own laws.</verse>
    <verse number="20" reference="Additions to Esther 6:20">And you shall aid them that they may kill those who had prepared themselves to kill them, on the thirteenth day of the twelfth month, which is called Adar.</verse>
    <verse number="21" reference="Additions to Esther 6:21">For the almighty God hath turned this day of sadness and mourning into joy to them.</verse>
    <verse number="22" reference="Additions to Esther 6:22">Wherefore you shall also count this day among other festival days, and celebrate it with all joy, that it may be known also in times to come,</verse>
    <verse number="23" reference="Additions to Esther 6:23">That all they who faithfully obey the Persians, receive a worthy reward for their fidelity: but they that are traitors to their kingdom, are destroyed for their wickedness.</verse>
    <verse number="24" reference="Additions to Esther 6:24">And let every province and city, that will not be partaker of this solemnity, perish by the sword and by fire, and be destroyed in such manner as to be made unpassable, both to men and beasts, for an example of contempt, and disobedience. THE BOOK OF JOB This Book takes its name from the holy man of whom it treats: who, according to the more probable opinion, was of the race of Esau; and the same as Jobab, king of Edom, mentioned Gen. 36.33. It is uncertain who was the writer of it. Some attribute it to Job himself; others to Moses, or some one of the prophets. In the Hebrew it is written in verse, from the beginning of the third chapter to the forty-second chapter. Job Chapter 1</verse>
    <verse number="25" reference="Additions to Esther 6:25">For the fear which I feared, hath come upon me: and that which I was afraid of, hath befallen me.</verse>
    <verse number="26" reference="Additions to Esther 6:26">Have I not dissembled? have I not kept silence?  have I not been quiet? and indignation is come upon me. Job Chapter 4</verse>
    <verse number="27" reference="Additions to Esther 6:27">Behold, this is even so, as we have searched out: which thou having heard, consider it thoroughly in thy mind. Job Chapter 6</verse>
    <verse number="28" reference="Additions to Esther 6:28">However, finish what you have begun: give ear and see whether I lie.</verse>
    <verse number="29" reference="Additions to Esther 6:29">Answer, I beseech you, without contention: and speaking that which is just, judge ye.</verse>
    <verse number="30" reference="Additions to Esther 6:30">And you shall not find iniquity in my tongue, neither shall folly sound in my mouth. Job Chapter 7</verse>
    <verse number="31" reference="Additions to Esther 6:31">Yet thou shalt plunge me in filth, and my garments shall abhor me.</verse>
    <verse number="32" reference="Additions to Esther 6:32">For I shall not answer a man that is like myself: nor one that may be heard with me equally in judgment.</verse>
    <verse number="33" reference="Additions to Esther 6:33">There is none that may be able to reprove both, and to put his hand between both.</verse>
    <verse number="34" reference="Additions to Esther 6:34">Let him take his rod away from me, and let not his fear terrify me.</verse>
    <verse number="35" reference="Additions to Esther 6:35">I will speak, and will not fear him: for I cannot answer while I am in fear. Job Chapter 10</verse>
    <verse number="36" reference="Additions to Esther 6:36">That I may carry it on my shoulder, and put it about me as a crown?</verse>
    <verse number="37" reference="Additions to Esther 6:37">At every step of mine I would pronounce it, and offer it as to a prince.</verse>
    <verse number="38" reference="Additions to Esther 6:38">If my land cry against me, and with it the furrows thereof mourn:</verse>
    <verse number="39" reference="Additions to Esther 6:39">If I have eaten the fruits thereof without money, and have afflicted the son of the tillers thereof:</verse>
    <verse number="40" reference="Additions to Esther 6:40">Let thistles grow up to me instead of wheat, and thorns instead of barley. The words of Job are ended. Job Chapter 32 Eliu is angry with Job and his friends. He boasts of himself.</verse>
    <verse number="41" reference="Additions to Esther 6:41">Who provideth food for the raven, when her young ones cry to God, wandering about, because they have no meat? Job Chapter 39 The wonders of the power and providence of God in many of his creatures.</verse>
    <verse number="42" reference="Additions to Esther 6:42">They cried, but there was none to save them, to the Lord: but he heard them not.</verse>
    <verse number="43" reference="Additions to Esther 6:43">And I shall beat them as small as the dust before the wind; I shall bring them to nought, like the dirt in the streets.</verse>
    <verse number="44" reference="Additions to Esther 6:44">Thou wilt deliver me from the contradictions of the people; thou wilt make me head of the Gentiles.</verse>
    <verse number="45" reference="Additions to Esther 6:45">A people which I knew not, hath served me: at the hearing of the ear they have obeyed me.</verse>
    <verse number="46" reference="Additions to Esther 6:46">The children that are strangers have lied to me, strange children have faded away, and have halted from their paths.</verse>
    <verse number="47" reference="Additions to Esther 6:47">The Lord liveth, and blessed by my God, and let the God of my salvation be exalted.</verse>
    <verse number="48" reference="Additions to Esther 6:48">O God, who avengest me, and subduest the people under me, my deliverer from my enraged enemies.</verse>
    <verse number="49" reference="Additions to Esther 6:49">And thou wilt lift me up above them that rise up against me: from the unjust man thou wilt deliver me.</verse>
    <verse number="50" reference="Additions to Esther 6:50">Therefore will I give glory to thee, O Lord, among the nations, and I will sing a psalm to thy name.</verse>
    <verse number="51" reference="Additions to Esther 6:51">Giving great deliverance to his king, and shewing mercy to David, his anointed: and to his seed for ever. Psalms Chapter 18 Coeli enarrant. The works of God shew forth his glory: his law is greatly to be esteemed and loved.</verse>
    <verse number="52" reference="Additions to Esther 6:52">And he took away his own people as sheep: and guided them in the wilderness like a flock.</verse>
    <verse number="53" reference="Additions to Esther 6:53">And he brought them out in hope and they feared not: and the sea overwhelmed their enemies.</verse>
    <verse number="54" reference="Additions to Esther 6:54">And he brought them into the mountain of his sanctuary: the mountain which his right hand had purchased. And he cast out the Gentiles before them: and by lot divided to them their land by a line of distribution.</verse>
    <verse number="55" reference="Additions to Esther 6:55">And he made the tribes of Israel to dwell in their tabernacles.</verse>
    <verse number="56" reference="Additions to Esther 6:56">Yet they tempted, and provoked the most high God: and they kept not his testimonies.</verse>
    <verse number="57" reference="Additions to Esther 6:57">And they turned away, and kept not the covenant: even like their fathers they were turned aside as a crooked bow.</verse>
    <verse number="58" reference="Additions to Esther 6:58">They provoked him to anger on their hills: and moved him to jealousy with their graven things.</verse>
    <verse number="59" reference="Additions to Esther 6:59">God heard, and despised them, and he reduced Israel exceedingly as it were to nothing.</verse>
    <verse number="60" reference="Additions to Esther 6:60">And he put away the tabernacle of Silo, his tabernacle where he dwelt among men.</verse>
    <verse number="61" reference="Additions to Esther 6:61">And he delivered their strength into captivity: and their beauty into the hands of the enemy.</verse>
    <verse number="62" reference="Additions to Esther 6:62">And he shut up his people under the sword: and he despised his inheritance.</verse>
    <verse number="63" reference="Additions to Esther 6:63">Fire consumed their young men: and their maidens were not lamented.</verse>
    <verse number="64" reference="Additions to Esther 6:64">Their priests fell by the sword: and their widows did not mourn.</verse>
    <verse number="65" reference="Additions to Esther 6:65">And the Lord was awaked as one out of sleep, and like a mighty man that hath been surfeited with wine.</verse>
    <verse number="66" reference="Additions to Esther 6:66">And he smote his enemies on the hinder parts: he put them to an everlasting reproach.</verse>
    <verse number="67" reference="Additions to Esther 6:67">And he rejected the tabernacle of Joseph: and chose not the tribe of Ephraim:</verse>
    <verse number="68" reference="Additions to Esther 6:68">But he chose the tribe of Juda, mount Sion which he loved.</verse>
    <verse number="69" reference="Additions to Esther 6:69">And he built his sanctuary as of unicorns, in the land which he founded for ever. As of unicorns... That is, firm and strong like the horn of the unicorn. This is one of the chiefest of the propositions of this psalm, foreshewing the firm establishment of the one, true, and everlasting sanctuary of God, in his church.</verse>
    <verse number="70" reference="Additions to Esther 6:70">And he chose his servant David, and took him from the flocks of sheep: he brought him from following the ewes great with young,</verse>
    <verse number="71" reference="Additions to Esther 6:71">To feed Jacob his servant and Israel his inheritance.</verse>
    <verse number="72" reference="Additions to Esther 6:72">And he fed them in the innocence of his heart: and conducted them by the skilfulness of his hands. Psalms Chapter 78 Deus, venerunt gentes. The church in time of persecution prayeth for relief. It seems to belong to the time of the Machabees.</verse>
    <verse number="73" reference="Additions to Esther 6:73">Thy hands have made me and formed me: give me understanding, and I will learn thy commandments.</verse>
    <verse number="74" reference="Additions to Esther 6:74">They that fear thee shall see me, and shall be glad: because I have greatly hoped in thy words.</verse>
    <verse number="75" reference="Additions to Esther 6:75">I know, O Lord, that thy judgments are equity: and in thy truth thou hast humbled me.</verse>
    <verse number="76" reference="Additions to Esther 6:76">O! let thy mercy be for my comfort, according to thy word unto thy servant.</verse>
    <verse number="77" reference="Additions to Esther 6:77">Let thy tender mercies come unto me, and I shall live: for thy law is my meditation.</verse>
    <verse number="78" reference="Additions to Esther 6:78">Let the proud be ashamed, because they have done unjustly towards me: but I will be employed in thy commandments.</verse>
    <verse number="79" reference="Additions to Esther 6:79">Let them that fear thee turn to me: and they that know thy testimonies.</verse>
    <verse number="80" reference="Additions to Esther 6:80">Let my heart be undefiled in thy justifications, that I may not be confounded. CAPH.</verse>
    <verse number="81" reference="Additions to Esther 6:81">My soul hath fainted after thy salvation: and in thy word I have very much hoped.</verse>
    <verse number="82" reference="Additions to Esther 6:82">My eyes have failed for thy word, saying: When wilt thou comfort me?</verse>
    <verse number="83" reference="Additions to Esther 6:83">For I am become like a bottle in the frost: I have not forgotten thy justifications.</verse>
    <verse number="84" reference="Additions to Esther 6:84">How many are the days of thy servant: when wilt thou execute judgment on them that persecute me?</verse>
    <verse number="85" reference="Additions to Esther 6:85">The wicked have told me fables: but not as thy law.</verse>
    <verse number="86" reference="Additions to Esther 6:86">All thy statutes are truth: they have persecuted me unjustly, do thou help me.</verse>
    <verse number="87" reference="Additions to Esther 6:87">They had almost made an end of me upon earth: but I have not forsaken thy commandments.</verse>
    <verse number="88" reference="Additions to Esther 6:88">Quicken thou me according to thy mercy: and I shall keep the testimonies of thy mouth. LAMED.</verse>
    <verse number="89" reference="Additions to Esther 6:89">For ever, O Lord, thy word standeth firm in heaven.</verse>
    <verse number="90" reference="Additions to Esther 6:90">Thy truth unto all generations: thou hast founded the earth, and it continueth.</verse>
    <verse number="91" reference="Additions to Esther 6:91">By thy ordinance the day goeth on: for all things serve thee.</verse>
    <verse number="92" reference="Additions to Esther 6:92">Unless thy law had been my meditation, I had then perhaps perished in my abjection.</verse>
    <verse number="93" reference="Additions to Esther 6:93">Thy justifications I will never forget: for by them thou hast given me life.</verse>
    <verse number="94" reference="Additions to Esther 6:94">I am thine, save thou me: for I have sought thy justifications.</verse>
    <verse number="95" reference="Additions to Esther 6:95">The wicked have waited for me to destroy me: but I have understood thy testimonies.</verse>
    <verse number="96" reference="Additions to Esther 6:96">I have seen an end of all perfection: thy commandment is exceeding broad. MEM.</verse>
    <verse number="97" reference="Additions to Esther 6:97">O how have I loved thy law, O Lord! it is my meditation all the day.</verse>
    <verse number="98" reference="Additions to Esther 6:98">Through thy commandment, thou hast made me wiser than my enemies: for it is ever with me.</verse>
    <verse number="99" reference="Additions to Esther 6:99">I have understood more than all my teachers: because thy testimonies are my meditation.</verse>
    <verse number="100" reference="Additions to Esther 6:100">I have had understanding above ancients: because I have sought thy commandments.</verse>
    <verse number="101" reference="Additions to Esther 6:101">I have restrained my feet from every evil way: that I may keep thy words.</verse>
    <verse number="102" reference="Additions to Esther 6:102">I have not declined from thy judgments, because thou hast set me a law.</verse>
    <verse number="103" reference="Additions to Esther 6:103">How sweet are thy words to my palate! more than honey to my mouth.</verse>
    <verse number="104" reference="Additions to Esther 6:104">By thy commandments I have had understanding: therefore have I hated every way of iniquity. NUN.</verse>
    <verse number="105" reference="Additions to Esther 6:105">Thy word is a lamp to my feet, and a light to my paths.</verse>
    <verse number="106" reference="Additions to Esther 6:106">I have sworn and am determined to keep the judgments of thy justice.</verse>
    <verse number="107" reference="Additions to Esther 6:107">I have been humbled, O Lord, exceedingly: quicken thou me according to thy word.</verse>
    <verse number="108" reference="Additions to Esther 6:108">The free offerings of my mouth make acceptable, O Lord: and teach me thy judgments.</verse>
    <verse number="109" reference="Additions to Esther 6:109">My soul is continually in my hands: and I have not forgotten thy law.</verse>
    <verse number="110" reference="Additions to Esther 6:110">Sinners have laid a snare for me: but I have not erred from thy precepts.</verse>
    <verse number="111" reference="Additions to Esther 6:111">I have purchased thy testimonies for an inheritance for ever: because they are the joy of my heart.</verse>
    <verse number="112" reference="Additions to Esther 6:112">I have inclined my heart to do thy justifications for ever, for the reward. SAMECH.</verse>
    <verse number="113" reference="Additions to Esther 6:113">I have hated the unjust: and have loved thy law.</verse>
    <verse number="114" reference="Additions to Esther 6:114">Thou art my helper and my protector: and in thy word I have greatly hoped.</verse>
    <verse number="115" reference="Additions to Esther 6:115">Depart from me, ye malignant: and I will search the commandments of my God.</verse>
    <verse number="116" reference="Additions to Esther 6:116">Uphold me according to thy word, and I shall live: and let me not be confounded in my expectation.</verse>
    <verse number="117" reference="Additions to Esther 6:117">Help me, and I shall be saved: and I will meditate always on thy justifications.</verse>
    <verse number="118" reference="Additions to Esther 6:118">Thou hast despised all them that fall off from thy judgments; for their thought is unjust.</verse>
    <verse number="119" reference="Additions to Esther 6:119">I have accounted all the sinners of the earth prevaricators: therefore have I loved thy testimonies.</verse>
    <verse number="120" reference="Additions to Esther 6:120">Pierce thou my flesh with thy fear: for I am afraid of thy judgments. AIN.</verse>
    <verse number="121" reference="Additions to Esther 6:121">I have done judgment and justice: give me not up to them that slander me.</verse>
    <verse number="122" reference="Additions to Esther 6:122">Uphold thy servant unto good: let not the proud calumniate me.</verse>
    <verse number="123" reference="Additions to Esther 6:123">My eyes have fainted after thy salvation: and for the word of thy justice.</verse>
    <verse number="124" reference="Additions to Esther 6:124">Deal with thy servant according to thy mercy: and teach me thy justifications.</verse>
    <verse number="125" reference="Additions to Esther 6:125">I am thy servant: give me understanding that I may know thy testimonies.</verse>
    <verse number="126" reference="Additions to Esther 6:126">It is time, O Lord, to do: they have dissipated thy law.</verse>
    <verse number="127" reference="Additions to Esther 6:127">Therefore have I loved thy commandments above gold and the topaz.</verse>
    <verse number="128" reference="Additions to Esther 6:128">Therefore was I directed to all thy commandments: I have hated all wicked ways. PHE.</verse>
    <verse number="129" reference="Additions to Esther 6:129">Thy testimonies are wonderful: therefore my soul hath sought them.</verse>
    <verse number="130" reference="Additions to Esther 6:130">The declaration of thy words giveth light: and giveth understanding to little ones.</verse>
    <verse number="131" reference="Additions to Esther 6:131">I opened my mouth, and panted: because I longed for thy commandments.</verse>
    <verse number="132" reference="Additions to Esther 6:132">Look thou upon me, and have mercy on me according to the judgment of them that love thy name.</verse>
    <verse number="133" reference="Additions to Esther 6:133">Direct my steps according to thy word: and let no iniquity have dominion over me.</verse>
    <verse number="134" reference="Additions to Esther 6:134">Redeem me from the calumnies of men: that I may keep thy commandments.</verse>
    <verse number="135" reference="Additions to Esther 6:135">Make thy face to shine upon thy servant: and teach me thy justifications.</verse>
    <verse number="136" reference="Additions to Esther 6:136">My eyes have sent forth springs of water: because they have not kept thy law. SADE.</verse>
    <verse number="137" reference="Additions to Esther 6:137">Thou art just, O Lord: and thy judgment is right.</verse>
    <verse number="138" reference="Additions to Esther 6:138">Thou hast commanded justice thy testimonies: and thy truth exceedingly.</verse>
    <verse number="139" reference="Additions to Esther 6:139">My zeal hath made me pine away: because my enemies forgot thy words.</verse>
    <verse number="140" reference="Additions to Esther 6:140">Thy word is exceedingly refined: and thy servant hath loved it.</verse>
    <verse number="141" reference="Additions to Esther 6:141">I am very young and despised; but I forget not thy justifications.</verse>
    <verse number="142" reference="Additions to Esther 6:142">Thy justice is justice for ever: and thy law is the truth.</verse>
    <verse number="143" reference="Additions to Esther 6:143">Trouble and anguish have found me: thy commandments are my meditation.</verse>
    <verse number="144" reference="Additions to Esther 6:144">Thy testimonies are justice for ever: give me understanding, and I shall live. COPH.</verse>
    <verse number="145" reference="Additions to Esther 6:145">I cried with my whole heart, hear me, O Lord: I will seek thy justifications.</verse>
    <verse number="146" reference="Additions to Esther 6:146">I cried unto thee, save me: that I may keep thy commandments.</verse>
    <verse number="147" reference="Additions to Esther 6:147">I prevented the dawning of the day, and cried: because in thy words I very much hoped.</verse>
    <verse number="148" reference="Additions to Esther 6:148">My eyes to thee have prevented the morning: that I might meditate on thy words.</verse>
    <verse number="149" reference="Additions to Esther 6:149">Hear thou my voice, O Lord, according to thy mercy: and quicken me according to thy judgment.</verse>
    <verse number="150" reference="Additions to Esther 6:150">They that persecute me have drawn nigh to iniquity; but they are gone far off from thy law.</verse>
    <verse number="151" reference="Additions to Esther 6:151">Thou art near, O Lord: and all thy ways are truth.</verse>
    <verse number="152" reference="Additions to Esther 6:152">I have known from the beginning concerning thy testimonies: that thou hast founded them for ever. RES.</verse>
    <verse number="153" reference="Additions to Esther 6:153">See my humiliation and deliver me for I have not forgotten thy law.</verse>
    <verse number="154" reference="Additions to Esther 6:154">Judge my judgment and redeem me: quicken thou me for thy word's sake.</verse>
    <verse number="155" reference="Additions to Esther 6:155">Salvation is far from sinners; because they have not sought thy justifications.</verse>
    <verse number="156" reference="Additions to Esther 6:156">Many, O Lord, are thy mercies: quicken me according to thy judgment.</verse>
    <verse number="157" reference="Additions to Esther 6:157">Many are they that persecute me and afflict me; but I have not declined from thy testimonies.</verse>
    <verse number="158" reference="Additions to Esther 6:158">I beheld the transgressors, and pined away; because they kept not thy word.</verse>
    <verse number="159" reference="Additions to Esther 6:159">Behold I have loved thy commandments, O Lord; quicken me thou in thy mercy.</verse>
    <verse number="160" reference="Additions to Esther 6:160">The beginning of thy words is truth: all the judgments of thy justice are for ever. SIN.</verse>
    <verse number="161" reference="Additions to Esther 6:161">Princes have persecuted me without cause: and my heart hath been in awe of thy words.</verse>
    <verse number="162" reference="Additions to Esther 6:162">I will rejoice at thy words, as one that hath found great spoil.</verse>
    <verse number="163" reference="Additions to Esther 6:163">I have hated and abhorred iniquity; but I have loved thy law.</verse>
    <verse number="164" reference="Additions to Esther 6:164">Seven times a day I have given praise to thee, for the judgments of thy justice.</verse>
    <verse number="165" reference="Additions to Esther 6:165">Much peace have they that love thy law, and to them there is no stumbling block.</verse>
    <verse number="166" reference="Additions to Esther 6:166">I looked for thy salvation, O Lord: and I loved thy commandments.</verse>
    <verse number="167" reference="Additions to Esther 6:167">My soul hath kept thy testimonies and hath loved them exceedingly.</verse>
    <verse number="168" reference="Additions to Esther 6:168">I have kept thy commandments and thy testimonies: because all my ways are in thy sight. TAU.</verse>
    <verse number="169" reference="Additions to Esther 6:169">Let my supplication, O Lord, come near in thy sight: give me understanding according to thy word.</verse>
    <verse number="170" reference="Additions to Esther 6:170">Let my request come in before thee; deliver thou me according to thy word.</verse>
    <verse number="171" reference="Additions to Esther 6:171">My lips shall utter a hymn, when thou shalt teach me thy justifications.</verse>
    <verse number="172" reference="Additions to Esther 6:172">My tongue shall pronounce thy word: because all thy commandments are justice.</verse>
    <verse number="173" reference="Additions to Esther 6:173">Let thy hand be with me to save me; for I have chosen thy precepts.</verse>
    <verse number="174" reference="Additions to Esther 6:174">I have longed for thy salvation, O Lord; and thy law is my meditation.</verse>
    <verse number="175" reference="Additions to Esther 6:175">My soul shall live and shall praise thee: and thy judgments shall help me.</verse>
    <verse number="176" reference="Additions to Esther 6:176">I have gone astray like a sheep that is lost: seek thy servant, because I have not forgotten thy commandments. Psalms Chapter 119 Ad Dominum. A prayer in tribulation. A gradual canticle. A gradual canticle... The following psalms, in number fifteen, are called gradual psalms, or canticles, from the word gradus, signifying steps, ascensions, or degrees: either because they were appointed to be sung on the fifteen steps, by which the people ascended to the temple: or, that in the singing of them the voice was to be raised by certain steps or ascensions: or, that they were to be sung by the people returning from their captivity and ascending to Jerusalem, which was seated amongst mountains. The holy fathers, in a mystical sense, understand these steps, or ascensions, of the degrees by which Christians spiritually ascend to virtue and perfection; and to the true temple of God in the heavenly Jerusalem.</verse>
  </chapter>
</book>
